Finding Aid for Boyd family papers, 1761-1945
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Boyd family papers 1761-1945
Boyd family.
1 linear foot
85498 Aa 2
William H. Boyd family of Monroe, Michigan. Correspondence, diaries, addresses, photograph, and miscellaneous papers concerning family and business affairs, temperance, slavery and the First Presbyterian Church of Monroe, Michigan. Correspondents include: Isaac P. Christiancy and Alpheus Felch.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Carrie L. Boyd (donor no. 1083 ) and came to the library in different accessions, 1937-1945.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
William H. Boyd was born in Hartwick, Otsego county, New York on October 6, 1811. He was educated at Ovid Academy and Rensselaer Institute, then returned to Ovid, New York where he worked with his father in his mercantile business. In 1836, he decided to move to Monroe, Michigan where he opened a dry goods business, to which he eventually added groceries, hardware and products.
In Monroe, Boyd continued his church activities begun in New York state. He joined the First Presbyterian Church and became active in the state Sunday School Association. He also attended national and international conventions of the association, and was a member and vice-president (1876) of the American Sunday School Union.
The Boyd family collection includes correspondence, diaries of family members, addresses, photographs, and miscellaneous papers concerning family and business affairs, temperance, slavery and the First Presbyterian Church of Monroe, Michigan. Correspondents include: Isaac P. Christiancy and Alpheus Felch.
Subjects:
Boyd family.; First Presbyterian Church (Monroe, Mich.); Monroe (Mich.); Women--Michigan--Monroe.; Presbyterian Church--Michigan--Monroe.; Antislavery movements--United States.; Temperance--Michigan--Monroe.; Boyd, Carrie Lucy, 1864-1949.; Boyd, Irving Payson, 1851-1923.; Boyd, William Augustus, 1785-1854.; Boyd, William H. (William Hart), 1811-1898.; Christiancy, Isaac Peckham, 1812-1890.; Felch, Alpheus, 1804-1896.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Boyd, Irving Payson, 1851-1923.; Boyd, William H. (William Hart), 1811-1898.; Boyd family.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1832-1859 (Box 1)
    (include letter from Alpheus Felch, April 21, 1848)
  - 1860-1869 (Box 1)
  - 1870-1878 (Box 1)
  - 1881-1884 (Box 1)
  - 1885-1889 (Box 1)
  - 1890-1899 (Box 1)
  - 1900-1904 (Box 1)
  - 1905-1910 (Box 1)
  - 1912-1945 (Box 1)
- Other papers
  - Genealogical material (Box 1)
  - Deeds and legal agreements, 1761-1855 (Box 1)
  - Notes of William H. Boyd while a student at Rensselaer School, 1832, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Speeches and notes of William H. Boyd (Box 1)
  - Addresses and notes on temperance by William H. Boyd (Box 1)
  - History of the Presbyterian Church of Monroe by Carrie Boyd (Box 1)
  - Presbyterian Church historical material (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous addresses and notes, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Photographs: portraits of family members and friends (Box 1)
  - Business ledger and cash book, 3 volumes (Box 1)
  - Scrapbooks, notebooks, expense book, etc. (Box 1)
  - Diaries
    - Diary of Irving Payson Boyd, 1865 (Box 1)
    - Diary of Carrie L. Boyd, 1876 (Box 1)